Without the slightest fear of making it more complicated than it already was.
This, my friends, is the equivalent of Tiktok but the opposite.
My name is Andreas Ekström and I am often found at Sydsvenskan but it is Lund University
And especially the Faculty of Social Sciences, which hosts debate in Lund.
Today's discussion is about language.
Cane horses you could say and you should not imagine anything
All of you who are here in this crowded hall, which cane horses did you ride here?
Anyone want to shout just?
What is your linguistic cane horse?
Judgment.
What did we have in the back?
Don't be shy now!
Specials yes!
You don't have to make it tonight anyway
Many of you certainly recognize Ola Wikander, who is an associate professor of Bible science
And expert in extinct language.
Welcome!
We are also very happy to have the linguist and the writer
For the book "Handbook for Language Police" here, Sara Lövestam!
Last but not least, experienced Swedish teacher from the Cathedral School, high school here in Lund,
Here we have Daniel Sandin, welcome!
You know what?
I actually assume that you love language.
You do that huh?
Why?
Something is it that has brought you
It has probably been a driving force,
Interest in the language.
But then it probably has come to be
How the language becomes the link to other people, how we understand each other.
From the dictionary and the different meanings of words, how you can perceive words
in different ways depending on which contexts,
which persons that pronounces them, in which meetings they occur to
How we interpret impendings in political communication.
So it has always been this link to others and how we understand each other.
Just that, what you say with political communication,
It has become a whole science
is some kind
Civil armor
which everyone should be trained in.
Yes, it is interesting because this is something that we have talked a lot about in other types of debates,
Thus, political polarization and media logic that we have also debated here in debate in Lund.
What the language does with one's understanding is something that we should go into deeper but also
where you place yourself as a human being, who do you then become as voter and
as a citizen.
We had another debate here that was about meritocracy,
Very much our students here at the university.
How do you qualify best if you think about one career in one or the other?
And so you have all this.
So yes, it is quite telling how much the language controls how you are perceived.
If you ever fight Daniel by motivating your students by plugging into the next sample,
Do you use the future argument a lot?
So because
See that this you need this, you will not be able to write good job applications,
You will not be able to write good home tentor.
I do that of course but I don't think they take it
because it lies like in the age of age and
The nature of youth not to really see those arguments.
But I am convinced, that is that
Builds my vision of what is incredibly important.
I want to give them, as we certainly come in at later, not to
back too much but really stand up to that it is so
Incredibly important
Being able to express oneself,
Incredibly important to master language
as they perceive is old -fashioned or passé.
For it provides access to arenas that
They may not even know that they will need it but they will need it.
But explaining to them that it is important is very difficult
Because they don't have the tools to understand it always.
Sometimes, sometimes not.
But sometimes I think that we don't understand either.
Just as you say, that's what we have.
A rather different language than they themselves are used to formulating these things in so it becomes
Some kind of double -speaking between that situation.
Just!
Then you have to have your own and be able to understand ...
One must be able to have the analytical scientific language running in the brain
While hearing the patient tell with other terminology.
It is a fairly sophisticated situation there.
This really applies to a lot of working groups.
You simply have to be an educator.
Ola, you said a word there, double -lust.
What was the nice word for that?
Diglossi.
Diglossi, then I have learned the first new words of the evening.
In the understanding of English words,
There, their understanding stood.
So that what happened was really the understanding of old Swedish words,
I have actually marked here
Which words went down the most.
Post, culvert strange enough,
withdrawal,
tedious,
warn,
exist.
So words like man ...
Bureaucratic embossed Germanic words.
In addition, but also as you can find in some news texts.
We had chosen words, we have not examined all the words but words that appear in newspapers,
So it was our selection criteria.
It is an important point that is because so fast
Someone thinks that now we'll make a reform about something
So there will always be some people who get stuck there.
There is one thing with the people who
mastered both for and after so well
so that they can only switch and, if necessary, switch back when they end up another social
context or in a more language conservative environment or whatever.
But those who get stuck, they are those who don't have
that double -speaking and can't do it.
And is told that no but now it is okay to write
What was not okay to write for a week.
Equalizer then.
Yes, a class equalizer but I think it risks going to just the opposite direction
because what it does is to
those who bring with them both the traditional and the easy -going can
swim lightly in those waters and know
easily how to switch between a
One style form to another for example, one spelling method to another.
But those who don't have it
marks directly what they end up and get no help with that
learn to navigate.
This sounds a bit like this classic argument from the left in Sweden to
Elegant formulated!
Okay, now we take it.
We just take it, we have to anyway, you understand that.
Okay, Anna.
They or them, how should we do?
I think we have already been into it.
I agree with this, somehow we can't start school.
We cannot start with the teachers stop teaching it, it must somehow start
from the other side.
I have no strong feelings about them and them, they!
It was a unique position in the debate, I must say that.
The name, the language changes and
Soon we will change
To them straight over.
It has been good in spoken language for maybe 100 years when we have not made a difference
And we have nevertheless understood each other.
And nothing is natural.
All this has to do with language ideological and language policy considerations
And that change has taken place has no moral implication in any way.
Which means we are in the unique situation that
We can choose and then I think we can well learn growing generations
To master that standard whether they speak as Finns or not.
Just that, for Finnish Swedes still do.
Well, not all but some do.
My grandmother who was very Scanian made the difference in speech.
But anyway,
What annoys me in this discussion it is when you make it
Like that there is some kind of pure automation,
that by the fact that
The majority speech has lost this distinction a long time ago,
Which is completely empirical correct, there is no discussion about it.
Thus, some kind of morality follows
to change the written language.
No!
It just doesn't!
Oh!
It holds against?
Absolutely!
And that is what I am committed to, this notion of an automatism.
But is it really a moral argument?
It is not rather about ...
Yes, but a little it is.
"You make it too difficult for the growing up ...".
In fact, 40 % of teachers have already stopped teaching elementary school or accepted this.
Then it is a choice they have made.
In addition, we can note that in the 80s, when I was a little PAG,
Then it was a lot of journalists who wrote them
And then they stopped it.
It is the same with the so-called modern spelling in the early 1900s
It is a very good example,
It lasted a few hundred years in writing after it began to die out in speech
And then someone made a decision and then it went pretty fast.
We have had spelling reforms of various kinds, even in other countries.
But now I also want to hear what Sara and Daniel say here, how should we do?
I don't really have strong feelings either, but I see it as we stand a little at a crossroads.
That either we release them freely
or so we get
plague
teaching both young and old and somehow
Start promotions, as well as a Swedish tiger size on that campaign
You can do this at home!
And then checked how many ...
It is a small ground, I only had a few hours on Sunday to do this but
on it turned out that there was not much difference in 2004 to 2022 except
in the case of a specific article.
Good audience!
There is a person at the front who said "I knew it!".
Well, for those who have temporarily forgotten a definite article,
So when you say
"The half -full glasses on the tables",
that, according to my little study, one
So it is more common to write now
not so many investigations into where it is heading with them and them
But there are surveys showing that those who become annoyed,
They become more annoyed at a misused they or them than a widely used judgment.
Can you match in passion Daniel?
How should we do?
I think I can match the passion actually ...
No, but like this: we might be at a crossroads but I think there is also that there is
Other perspectives on this.
It's not just them and them, it pretty much in the language
which is difficult.
I mean, it's not very hard to learn the difference between them and them,
Apart from your academic colleague.
But most people who have reasonable knowledge of the language handle it, it is not very strange.
What is required are teachers who teach the young people, the children,
to manage subject and object forms in writing.
It's no stranger than that.
The problem is something else that I see it,
That it becomes like an educational issue.
That we have such a large proportion early in elementary school
Teachers who themselves do not master them and them.
Then you are facing a crossroads.
Should we resign one because we have a teaching profession ...
I know, I stand out
Hakan here a bit as a teacher but I think ...
If so many
Teacher do not manage themselves and them
Without choosing to write them, it is clear that the children will write them.
So you get up to high school and so:
"Yes, we always had to write them, it went well ..."
I just mean that it's a question
And when we talk about these stuff we talk, I mean the SJ sounds,
Why should we spell the SJ sounds in seventy-eleven different ways?
It's pretty hard to learn.
Not for us anymore because we have learned but for the children, our only generation of young people
Must learn every word with spelling about it ...
Yes, you know how many SJ sound it is.
After all, it was a bit tricky, there are no direct rules.
But this is also associated with another thing,
Namely, the learning of what usually becomes our third language in Swedish.
Because if you can't these basic grammatical things
Do you get pretty tough to learn German if you try to do it when you are sixteen
Or that's when you get it.
Now, not many people have read German, I do not know how it is right now,
But at least it's my experience that
That's when you learned grammar when you started reading German.
Or Spanish or French.
Because it was not needed in the same way, it is not necessary for one's own native language in the same way.
I think Saras
Students at the writing courses who want to write in English, do they have problems with They and TheM?
It really is no big question really
But there is quite a lot else that comes with
And maybe there are signs of something we don't want, I think.
Like a view of education, language.
Because it is not just remove your
Back compatibility as well.
By removing them and them we also give a whole new generation
It is more difficult to read everything that is written back in time.
There are such aspects, in the same way as we would pie SJ sounds
If we remove them because it's so hard
for young people to learn.
Because that is the only argument for removing, because it is a bit difficult.
Not only, it is also that we do not make that distinction in speech.
I listened to Mumin, it was wonderful but I know it's a minority Finnish Swede
But it is still honest.
You Ola, I am fascinated by saying, crossroads you agree,
But Ola said we are in a election situation as well.
Because something none of you have said
but as one often hears in the debate it is
"But they are unstoppable, it will still be so."
That is, that is what we can call the cannabis argument,
But I don't look at it.
I have flirted with that argument but then I do not think it is a natural force
Without me, I think more according to our tradition of language changes.
That the Swedish language has often chosen
the road that follows the spoken language.
It is a remarkable conservative position you take now.
Exactly, I was just going to say that on the contrary,
that the one who says no in this,
Now we shall stop following the spoken language in writing
As we have always done, well then is denn
the person quite radical and does not follow the traditional as we have done
Important years for the language police ...
1943 it is Dagens Nyheter that slips the verb plural forms and
Soon all the other major newspapers follow.
But that's big is when TT does it in 1945.
How does such an old form sound?
Well, yes but it is, for example, instead of saying the drops drops
As we do now,
If you say the drops drop.
We still have this in our Christmas songs, among other things, we come instead of us.
Crayfish require these drinks.
Just!
These are the old plural forms that were removed under certain frame screams
Especially 1945 when TT, the newspapers' telegram agency, assumed that they would now ...
There is a great fun submitter in the Trelleborg Post from 1945 about it
And then people had
not talked so on a long time and
that it would have been pretty good about people
In school today learned to passively understand how those forms work
because we have so much literature written with that form of form
And then you can also avoid such
I school and things that hurt the soul when you hear.
It should be a star in a book I have!
Yes and the thing is that as this was so conservative thing under
So many years we have a huge literature that is written so and
It would have been pretty good to teach perhaps to high school students a quick overview of how this works
Because they will be confronted with something that is written like this.
I can say not only when they read
Strindberg without,
If they do now.
I teach in classic Hebrew and our grammar is written
Collection text written in this way
And you can actually learn things without writing yourself.
You can learn it as a literary ...
But it is fashionable to write about books now.
Last today the message came all Ian Fleming's Bond books will be cleaned up
From inappropriate languages and such.
But it becomes such a debate every time, because it is often about political things.
Now it was about the author Roald Dahl's books, that one would clean up in them,
Then there was a big frame scream everywhere.
Today, in a small note in Dagens Nyheter, the news will have the publishers have thought after
And should release both versions.
Yes, they should give out double.
Then no one reacts.
It's so upsetting!
Now everyone believes that now PK fascism has struck and so get 90 % of those who believe that
Now not that there was a language policy discussion that resulted in a compromise.
It does not reach out because it is not mass media enough and it ends with a note.
But that we write about and modernize children's books into a language like ...
So, it's not just that the plural forms disappear,
It is also that the vocabulary changes and it is no wonder.
We have made new Bible translations for the Bible to go and understand by modern ...
Not just why but partly.
No but partly and there is nothing controversial about this,
You replace words that are political and then there will be rebellions.
I also have to take a small lap and this has to do with one of your texts Sara
where you, and I think it was so good because I agree,
This is how the contemporary man works.
I appreciate the word "hen" very much,
Like a gathering pronoun.
It's very
It is noticed that they also usually slip, so to speak.
It usually tires with a man from time to time because you are so used to it
And because not means anything!
I get elite there, that is, I think they are a good thing
But you have not taken, this has Sara Lövestam taught me,
There are two words that mean, it's called homonym, and then I get totally crazy
Of that and Mello, it's my other such cane horse ...
But then I'll say, I'm for Mello!
Are you?!
Me too.
Yes and it is a very common way to shorten words and names of things.
Why are people so crazy about discussing language?
I mean in a positive sense too!
Are we passionate about this?
But it does not go back to what we started to talk about, that it is human.
This is why it is so important that
Language is allowed to live,
That we do not let language die out.
That people are allowed to speak their mother tongue and so on.
It is so incredibly close associated with who I am.
Therefore, it becomes part of the identity.
I was called radical because I think something, when you said not radical
but radical position but then I sat and thought
to hold on to them and them, yes but it becomes like part of an identity to think
Something about the language, it becomes one of me as a human being and how I express myself.
It was a small groove.
But how I express myself,
That's why.
It says something about who I am.
You wrote something before the debate, about language, about expressing oneself in a way so one is perceived
Smarter than you really are.
I thought it was so hard on because that's what it's all about, to be able to
formulate themselves, somehow
get into an environment.
For me, the language has been
part of the
My journey into the academic, in that environment.
To be able to
Navigate there and make it successful.
I know that when I write
So I will often reach.
I will often get
She writes to everyone.
I am both on the radio on the international and so TV4 and SVT so I get mail from different directions.
There is a woman who is very committed to that it is not called humans
Without it named people
and she writes to everyone
editors and points out that journalists are now able to talk properly.
This is a bit of a thing that I included in "Handbook for Language Police"
Too very often it is about there is a dialectal or ancient Swedish foundation for
Lots of what is considered language errors today.
It's a bit charming that someone attacks
A "language error" that is actually Stockholm.
Because it usually goes the other way.
It's not just Stockholm, this with you.
No, but among other things.
There is otherwise one
very scattered performance that as one speaks in
Stockholm that's right, which is - yes ...
But why people get so committed I think is about,
Now that I have immersed myself in this language police behavior,
It is that, yes, people go around and do this, they correct each other unpaid.
This something they feel is so important that they do this, you might risk their relationships,
one is not afraid of bad mood but you really want to say that it is not called
"Where are you?".
I think this is related to what I said first, the language is
nothing but an agreement
between all people who speak this language.
Up to 13 million who know Swedish to some extent in the world, we shall agree
and do we not agree on what words mean and how to formulate,
which ones should in which order,
Where it means ...
So this whole grammar
And the semantics.
If we do not agree then we cannot communicate.
After all, we are a large herd animal that has the opportunity to form huge flocks.
We can form larger flocks than any other animal on earth
by allowing us to communicate with each other.
Then communications fall, then we fall.
That was as dramatic as I almost spoke English!
I also want to think ...
Some kind of group thought there ....
My point has not even arrived.
It is not just agreement but it is also
The language is not just a means of communication, it is obviously,
But the language has for a long time in human history been an active art object that
man, whether you really want to admit it or not, are seen as a stone that has to be plastered
To become a beautiful statue or a house or what you want to build with it.
It makes that when you hear someone say or even more when you see someone write because
Language Art is largely in writing about an exclusively,
so it becomes for some people then provocative
When one sees something that
violates what one experiences as an imagined path to some kind of beauty
And maybe even more so when it happens inadvertently.
It is one thing with the syntax uprising and such because then you see that it is conscious
Yes but take it another lap.
I do, it goes well.
Be a bit active with your vocabulary
And find out, if you find out once, you have it later.
Anyone else who wants to throw away with something?
I can link, I think exactly the same.
If you buy the idea that it is better to know two words than one word,
That it makes one a better communicator, so three words must be better than two.
It almost becomes a ...
It means that 10,000 words
is better than 5 and 40 better than and so on.